Lily McIlroy Russell papers, Inclusive: 1897-1968; Bulk: 1942-1958
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Lily McIlroy Russell papers
Inclusive: 1897-1968; Bulk: 1942-1958
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
717
Russell, Lily McIlroy, 1887 - 1958
35 document boxes.
The Lily McIlroy Russell papers are composed of Russell's personal collected materials, literary productions, photographs, and personal correspondence. Much of the material is connected in some way with her longtime work at Baylor University.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Lily McIlroy Russell (1887-1958) was born in Kerrville, Texas, on 1887 January 24. Her father, Reverend Chester A. McIlroy, moved the family to New Mexico after the death of his wife, Mary Francis Laro McIlroy. After several years of living in New Mexico, the Russell family moved to Oklahoma and eventually Waco, Texas.
Lily Russell attended Baylor University where she received her bachelor and master's degrees in 1911 and 1931, respectively. Her family ties to Baylor reach back at least one or more generations, as her father attended Baylor University in Independence. Prior to joining the faculty at Baylor as an instructor in English, she taught at Baylor Academy from 1912 to 1917. Russell taught English at Baylor for five years.
On 1917 May 4 she married Junius Brownrigg Russell; they had one daughter, Mary Claudia Russell, and an unnamed son who presumably died at birth. Lily Russell and Junius Russell later divorced at an unknown date.
Lily Russell moved to Oregon in 1924 December, but returned to Baylor in 1926. That same year, she became an assistant to the Dean of Women. President Pat Neff appointed her as the Dean of Women in 1931, a position she held for the next nine years. In 1940 Russell became the Director of Public Relations, and served eight years in that role. As director, she chaired the Baylor Centennial Committee. She also served as Dean of the Union Building. Outside of Baylor, she was also a member of the William Tryon Chapter of the Daughters of the Republic of Texas, the American Association of American Women, and the Waco Convention Bureau. Her final position at Baylor was as official university historian, starting in 1950. In her capacity as historian, she worked closely with Frank Burkhalter and others in the Baylor Historical Society, as they worked to preserve Baylor University history. Lily Russell died on 1958 August 21 following complications of a broken hip. She was buried in Oakwood Cemetery next to her unnamed son.
Upon her death, her dream of writing a book on the history of Baylor University was carried out by Baylor employees Lois Smith Douglas Murray Strain and Sue Moore, who used her files to write Baylor at Independence.
Scope and Content
This collection contains Russell's personal collected materials, literary productions, photographs, and personal correspondence. Much of the material is connected in some way with her longtime work at Baylor University. The two largest series are Alumni Files and Correspondence. The collection starts prior to Russell's hiring at Baylor University as Assistant Dean of Women in 1929 and continues past her 1958 death into the mid-1960s. Following Russell's death, her secretaries continued to add to her personal files and her colleagues continued her work of writing a history of Baylor University. All series are in good condition.
The alumni files were compiled by Russell and her secretaries starting around 1942, while Russell was Director of Public Relations, and continued up to her death while she was Baylor's official university historian. Upon her death, Russell's primary secretary Dulce Ware continued adding to these files until the mid-1960s. Russell saw her work at Baylor University as gaining a "lifetime full of Baylor history children." Russell kept in constant contact with Baylor missionaries, writers, artists, educators, and politicians. By keeping up to date with the activities of notable Baylor graduates, Russell sought to write a book on vocations and another book celebrating the centennial of the Baylor University Volunteer Band.
Arrangement
The Lily McIlroy Russell papers had been organized prior to this finding aid, but with no inventory of the final collection or existing finding aid. It was not clear if this arrangement was in the original order or imposed by an archivist upon accession. Arrangement and titles were derived from the existing materials. In order to enhance access, minor alterations were made and those changes are noted in the finding aid.
Currently, there are five series in this collection: I. Alumni Files, II. Correspondence, III. Literary Productions, IV. Collected Materials, and V. Photographs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 717. Acquired 1974-06-17
Related Resources
Items in related collections
BU Records: Dean of the Union Building (Lily Russell), Inclusive: 1936-1966, Bulk: 1946-1954
BU Records: Historical Research Office, Inclusive: 1863-1974, undated, Bulk: 1944-1960, undated
Related references
Brassart, Amy. "Lily Russell: A Baylor Beauty." HESA Baylor History Project. Accessed 2017 January 6.
BU Records: Dean of the Union Building (Lily Russell), Accession #BU/161, The Texas Collection, Baylor University. Accessed 2016 November 18.
BU Records: Historical Research Office Records, Accession #BU/103, The Texas Collection, Baylor University. Accessed 2016 November 18.
Find A Grave Inc. "Lily McIlroy Russell." Memorial #129551443. Databases. Accessed 2016 November 18.
"Lily McIlroy Russell." In The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas, edited by Dayton Kelley. Waco: Texian Press, 1972.
Osborne, Catherine. "Just Ask Mrs. Russell, She Knows." The Daily Lariat. 1951 January 25. Accessed 2016 November 18.
Wallace, Patricia Ward. “Baylor’s Women.” In A Spirit So Rare: A History Of The Women Of Waco. Austin: Nortex Press, 1984.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Russell, Lily McIlroy, 1887-.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- Students.
Subjects
Baptist associations -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Baptists -- Missions.; Women -- Education (Higher) -- Texas -- Waco.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts.; Outlines (documents); Photographs.; Programs.; Speeches.
- Alumni Files, 1857-1968; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series was created by Lily McIlroy Russell and posthumously by her secretary, Dulce Ware. It spans Russell's various positions held at Baylor University, as the bulk of the files are from 1942 to 1958. Dulce Ware continued compiling these alumni files following Russell's death in 1958, causing many of the files to date up to the late 1960s. The files cover many of the academic areas and professions that Baylor University offers to its graduates. The majority of the files are focused on missionaries from Baylor, as Russell was asked to collect artifacts from missionaries for the newly-built Tidwell Bible Building, write a book on vocations, and ask former Volunteer Band members to submit their work to a publication for the centennial commemoration of the Volunteer Band.
  Russell filed her alumni files by broad category title, often by a more specific subcategory as well, and then the name of the subject file. These original file titles have been kept to preserve Russell's original intent. Often extra information, such as the location of a missionary, was also written on the file title. This information has now been included in the file itself.
  This series is in good condition, with minor rips and tears.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - The Arts-Actors (drama), 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Arts-Drawing and Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Arts-Musicians, 1941-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business and Industry-Businessmen, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business and Industry-Business Woman, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, A-B, 1944-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, Boone, Joseph Prince, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, C-G, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, Hyatt, J, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, H-N, 1943-1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, O-Z, 1941-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Church-Denominational Leaders, Robinson, Jackie, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Church-Missionaries-Abbott, John and Mrs., 1948-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Church-Missionaries-Adair, Mrs. J.B., 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Church-Missionaries-Alexander, Charlotte, 1943-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Church-Missionaries-Anderson, Parks Harris, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bagby, A.I. and Mrs., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bagby, W.B., 1941-1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bagby, T.C., 1941-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Church-Missionaries-Baker, Dwight L., 19501-1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bartley, James W. and Mrs., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Church-Missionaries-Beddoe, Dr. Robert E., 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bell, Paul C., 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Church-Missionaries-Blair, Martin S., 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Church-Missionaries-Blair, Judson W., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bowden, Beulah, 1946-1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bryan, Charles W., Mrs., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bryan, Dr. and Mrs. E.K., 1945-1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bryan, Dr. and Mrs. John R., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Church-Missionaries-Buckner, H.F., 1944-1956 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Church-Missionaries-Bush, Richard, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cammack, Pauline, 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church-Missionaries-Carlisle, A.B., 1897-1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cannata, Sam R., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cauthen, Baker J. and Mrs., 1944-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Church-Missionaries-Chaney, Edith, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Church-Missionaries-Chiu, Katherine Wong, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Church-Missionaries-Clifton, R.A. and Mrs., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Church-Missionaries-Clinkscales, Ernest R., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cody, Bill and Mrs., 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cole, Edward L. and Mrs., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cotten, Scott, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Church-Missionaries-Coupland, Laura H., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cowsert, Mrs. J.J., 1945-1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cox, Eric and Helen, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cozzens, Katherine, 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Church-Missionaries-Crabtree, Mildred, 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Church-Missionaries-Crawley, Winston, Mrs., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cross, Mrs. E.M., 1947-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Church-Missionaries-Crouch, E.H. and Mrs., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Church-Missionaries-Culpepper, Charles L. Jr., 1946-1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Church-Missionaries-Culpepper, Charles L. Sr., 1944-1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Church-Missionaries-Culpepper, H.H. and Mrs., 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Church-Missionaries-Cunningham, M.E. and Mrs., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Church-Missionaries-Currie, Mrs. Frances M., 1950 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Church-Missionaries-Daniel, C.D. and Mrs., undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Church-Missionaries-Daniel, J.C. and Mrs., 1914-1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Church-Missionaries-David, Nannie Bland, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Church-Missionaries-David, V.L., 1945-1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Church-Missionaries-Deter, A.B., 1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Church-Missionaries-Donath, A.C. and Mrs., 1944-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Church-Missionaries-Dosher, Edward P. and Mrs., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Church - Missionaries - Duff, W.H., 1942-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Church-Missionaries-Edwards, Mrs. Roberta Cox, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Church-Missionaries-Edwards, T.K., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Church-Missionaries-Elliott, Darline, 1943-1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Church-Missionaries-Englemann, Lorenz, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Church-Missionaries-Embry, Mrs. W.H., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1909-1958; 2
  This series contains materials on both Russell's professional life and personal life. Often, these two consistently intermingled, for her personal life greatly involved her duties at Baylor and her friends and colleagues from Baylor. Russell's correspondence begins before her initial assignment at Baylor as Assistant Dean of Women in 1929 and continues past her death in 1958. It contains letters from her friends, family members, colleagues, and several presidents of Baylor University.
  Russell's correspondence to Baylor alumni documents the university's growth and development through the years. She consistently describes life on campus, new construction, capital campaigns, and the university's enrollment numbers.
  This series is in good condition. Russell's correspondence has minor rips and tears.
  - Mailing Lists - American Association of University Women (AAUW), 1934-1947 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Mailing Lists, 1940-1941 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Model Letters (personal), undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Personal, 1946-1958 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Personal A-Z (1 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Personal A-Z (2 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Personal A-Z (3 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - General, 1943-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - General, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - General, 1909-1915 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - General, 1925-1929 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - General (1 of 2), 1930-1939 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - General (2 of 2), 1930-1939 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - General, 1940-1949 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - General (1 of 2), 1950-1957 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - General (2 of 2), 1950-1957 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Family Tree, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Public Relations Letterhead, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Greetings (1 of 2), 1946-1958 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Greetings (2 of 2), 1946-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - General (1 of 2), 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - General (2 of 2), 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Russell, 1931-1957 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Clyde (Irene Marshall) King (1 of 2), 1929-1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Mrs. Clyde (Irene Marshall) King (2 of 2), 1929-1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Mrs. Clyde (Irene Marshall) King (1 of 2), 1926-1936 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Mrs. Clyde (Irene Marshall) King (2 of 2), 1926-1936 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - C.A. McIlroy, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Minnie D. McIlroy, 1939-1958 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Patrick Morris Neff, 1929-1947 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - C.A. Russell, 1909-1935 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. C.A Russell, 1897-1916 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Junius Russell, 1916-1944 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Mary Claudia Russell (1 of 2), 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Mary Claudia Russell (2 of 2) (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Woman's Missionary Union (WMU) (1 of 2), 1941-1946 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Woman's Missionary Union (WMU) (2 of 2), 1941-1946 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - W.M.U., 1939-1952 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Christian Education (1 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Christian Education (2 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Christian Education (3 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - W.M.U. Contribution to Citizenship, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence A-E (1 of 3), 1936-1947 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence A-E (2 of 3), 1936-1947 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence A-E (3 of 3), 1936-1947 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence F-M (1 of 3), 1941-1947 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence F-M (2 of 3), 1941-1947 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence F-M (3 of 3), 1941-1947 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence N-Z (1 of 3), 1940-1947 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence N-Z (2 of 3), 1940-1947 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence N-Z (3 of 3), 1940-1947 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence (Transfer) (1 of 3), 1934-1940 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence (Transfer) (2 of 3), 1934-1940 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - W.M.U. Correspondence (Transfer) (3 of 3), 1934-1940 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - W.M.U. Education Chairman Reports (1 of 3), 1941-1946 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - W.M.U. Education Chairman Reports (2 of 3), 1941-1946 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - W.M.U. Education Chairman Reports (3 of 3), 1941-1946 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Encampments (1 of 2), 1942-1947 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Encampments (2 of 2), 1942-1947 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Encampments (1 of 2), 1941-1945 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Encampments (2 of 2), 1941-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Programs (1 of 2), 1943-1947 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Programs (2 of 2), 1943-1947 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Personal-A (1 of 2), 1939-1958 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Personal-A (2 of 2), 1939-1958 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Personal-B (1 of 3), 1933-1957 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Personal-B (2 of 3), 1933-1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Personal-B (3 of 3), 1933-1957 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Personal-C (1 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Personal-C (2 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Personal-C (3 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Personal-D (1 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Personal-D (2 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Personal-D (3 of 3), 1940-1958 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Personal-E-F (1 of 2), 1942-1957 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Personal-E-F (2 of 2), 1942-1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Personal-G (1 of 2), 1939-1958 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Personal-G (2 of 2), 1939-1958 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Personal-H (1 of 2), 1940-1957 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Personal-H (2 of 2), 1940-1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Personal-I, 1942-1958 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Personal-J, 1938-1943 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Personal-K, 1940-1956 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Personal-L, 1941-1958 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Personal-M (1 of 3), 1939-1957 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Personal-M (2 of 3), 1939-1957 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Personal-M (3 of 3), 1939-1957 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Personal-N, 1940-1957 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Personal-O, 1939-1953 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Personal-P, 1941-1955 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Personal-R (1 of 3), 1941-1958 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Personal-R (2 of 3), 1941-1958 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Personal-R (3 of 3), 1941-1958 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Personal-S (1 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Personal-S (2 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Personal-S (3 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Personal-T, 1939-1957 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Personal-U, 1941 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Personal-V, 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Personal-W (1 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Personal-W (2 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Personal-W (3 of 3), 1939-1958 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Personal-Y, 1940-1951 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Personal-Z, 1944 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Greetings (1 of 2), 1946-1958 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Greetings (2 of 2), 1946-1958 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Christmas Card Lists, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Literary Productions, undated; 3
  The series of Literary Productions is composed of writings Russell produced for Baylor University and those she wrote for personal enjoyment. While Russell's death prevented her finishing the history of Baylor University, several of her initial chapters and many of her notes are included in this series.
  All of her literary productions are undated. This series is in good condition, with minor rips and tears.
  - Literary Productions (1 of 3), undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions (2 of 3), undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Literary Productions (3 of 3), undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - History of Baylor University outline, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Incomplete Manuscript-Baylor University, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - "What the Church Means to Me", undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Short Stories (1 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Short Stories (2 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Short Stories (3 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Autobiography (1 of 2), undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Autobiography (2 of 2), undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Baylor's History (1 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Baylor's History (2 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Baylor's History (3 of 3), undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - "My Tussie Mussie", undated (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Speech Notes (1 of 3), undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Speech Notes (2 of 3), undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Speech Notes (3 of 3), undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Collected Materials, 1905-1968; 4
  The series contains Russell's personal collected materials, including W.M.U. programs, address lists, several Bibles, a bound copy of her master's thesis, datebooks, calendars, and most importantly, her collected notes and correspondence on Henry Lee Graves, the first president of Baylor University.
  This series is in good condition, except for the Bibles which are in poor condition. One is missing a front cover and the leather binding and covers are on others are flaking off.
  - Student Union Building, 1940-1948, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Teaching/Baylor Contracts, 1923-1948 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - University Record, 1926-1927 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - General, 1913, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - General, 1918-1957, undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - General, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Speech Materials, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Mary Claudia Russell Baylor Grades [RESTRICTED], 1945-1952 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - General, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1930-1940, undated (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - W.M.U. Programs (1 of 2), 1941-1944, undated (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - W.M.U. Programs (2 of 2), 1941-1944, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - W.M.U. Programs (1 of 2), 1929-1937 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - W.M.U. Programs (2 of 2), 1929-1937 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - W.M.U. Programs (1 of 2), 1940-1946 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - W.M.U. Programs (2 of 2), 1940-1946 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - W.M.U. Texas Officers, undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Personal (1 of 2), 1934-1957 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Personal (2 of 2), 1934-1957 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Gardening Notes, 1951, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Mailing Lists, 1956 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - University Extension Courses, 1938-1941 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Daughters of the Republic of Texas (1 of 3), 1936-1941 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Daughters of the Republic of Texas (2 of 3), 1936-1941 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Daughters of the Republic of Texas (3 of 3), 1936-1941 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - General, 1949-1955, undated (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Henry Lee Graves (1 of 3), undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Henry Lee Graves (2 of 3), undated (Box 29, Folder 2)